曾有人
Once there was a man
想要找出地球的真年g
who went searching for the true age of the earth.
^他的努力
In his struggles to discover it,
他o意glF了一O大的威he stumbled on a grave threat.
1966年 加州 帕_迪Beautiful spring day, Pasadena, California. 1966.
人安居I
Business is booming, life's good.
只有一人
Except for one man,
名叫克R・彼得森的地|化W家
a geochemist named Clair Patterson,
朋友叫他派特
known as Pat.
他J樗所看到的所有人都身於o形的威He knows that everyone he sees is in danger from an invisible menace.
他Q心要阻止@一切
And he's determined to put a stop to it,
不代r
no matter what the cost.
宇宙大探索
第七集
榱艘f清楚彼得森的故事
You can't really tell Pat Patterson's story
必要暮芫煤芫靡郧暗厍蛘Q生前f起
without going all the way back to the time long before the earth our home, was built,
那r星星a生它的物|
when the stars brought forth its substance.
F
Iron
砹诵行堑群
For the planet's molten core.
氧
Oxygen.
砹搜沂 水和空
For the rocks and the water and the air.
碳
Carbon.
砹髓石和生命
For diamonds. And life.
一w星Q生了
A star is born,
我的星球
ours.
最初的装偃f年Y 一切算利
For the first few million years, things ran smoothly
m土w粒L雪球般的逐u成更大的物w
as dust grains snowballed into progressively larger objects.
直到@物w大到一定程度
But once these objects grew massive enough
有了足虻囊力
to have sufficient gravity,
它_始相互吸引 亩道相交相撞
they began pulling each other into crossing orbits.
@就是我的世界最初的模
This is how our world looked when it was new.
地球表面]有地方可以免於y
No part of the earth's surface could survive intact
一直到F在
from that time to the present.
既然地球的幼年都不痛嬖诹
So, with all its birth and early childhood records erased,
我怎N才能_定地球真正的年o呢
how could we ever hope to know with any certainty the true age of our world?
@是自古以淼闹i
People have been wondering about this since antiquity.
1650年 m大主教詹姆斯・
In 1650 archbishop James Ussher of Ireland
得出一貌似正_的Y
made a calculation that seemed to settle the question.
就和r大多等艘
Like almost everyone else of his time and his world,
他的根是}的造物
he accepted the biblical account of creation as authoritative.
但是}Y也]有提到具w的年代
But the Bible does not give exact years,
於是在fs中ふ乙
so Ussher searched for an event in the Old Testament
c已知v史事件相吻合的rg
that corresponded to a known historical date.
他在列王下卷中lF了
He found it in the second book of kings,
巴比y治者尼布甲尼撒二世死於公元前562年
the death of the Babylonian ruler Nebuchadnezzar in 562 B.C.
⑹来的先知和族L加起
Usher added up the generations of the prophets and the Patriarchs,
fs中的139族V
the 139 "Begats" of the Old Testament,
一直到尼布甲尼撒二世
between Adam and the time of Nebuchadnezzar,
他lF
and discovered
@世界Q生於10月22
that the world began on October 22
公元前4004年
in the year 4004 B.C.
下午六c
At 6:00 P.M.
星期六
It was a Saturday.
大主教制定的年表在r的西方被奉檎胬
Archbishop Ussher's chronology was taken as gospel in the Western world.
直到我通^另一N途讲t解地球的年o
Until we turned to another book to find the age of the earth,
通^研究岩石本身的
the one that was written in the rocks themselves.
科_拉多大Most of the rock layers in the walls of the Grand Canyon
都凫冻练e岩 由S多小的w粒堆e而成
are made of sediments, deposited as fine grains
@些沉e岩形成的r候 @Y是海洋
in a time when this part of the world was a sea.
年鸵荒 沉e物被不嘣黾拥男鲁练e物嚎s成了岩石
Over eons, the sediments were compressed into rock under the weight of succeeding layers,
最下面的就是最古老的
with the oldest ones at the bottom.
S便x一
Pick a layer, any layer.
那怎N
How about that one?
很久以前 @Y水K不深
Once upon a time, there must have been shallow water here.
在前寒武or期
Back in the Precambrian period,
大s10|年前
about a billion years ago,
那r只有一N生物
there was only one kind of life.
@些These blue-green bacteria were busy harvesting sunlight
亩a生氧
and making oxygen.
λ碚f那只是U
For them, it was just a waste product,
但於後淼游 包括我碚f
but for the animals who evolved later, including us,
那是孕育生命的呼吸
it was the breath of life.
另x一
Okay. Pick another layer.
那怎N
How about that one?
@颖环Q楣饷魈焓鬼岩
This layer is known as the bright angel shale.
形成於5.3|年前
It formed about 530 million years ago.
@些足E凫2.6|年前
These tracks were left 260 million years ago.
你想知道地球的年o
So you want to know the age of the earth?
只要t解形成每一铀需的rg
Just figure out how long it took to deposit each layer
不需要把族V加起
and then, instead of counting the "Begats,"
把@些哟渭悠砭蛄
add up all the layers.
很伟
Easy, right?
有一} 我是根^察@^程得出的Y
Just one problem, We know from observing this process,
因樗在持m
because it still happens today
在海洋中 在湖泊中
in oceans and lakes around the world.
沉e拥男纬rgL度各不相同
That sediments can be laid down at widely different rates.
通常都是非常的慢
It usually happens very slowly,
大s1000年才有1英尺
say a foot of sediment per 1,000 years.
但如果l生了罕的大洪
But when the's a rare catastrophic flood,
速度就快很多
it can happen much faster,
滋炀鸵呀有1英尺了
as much as a foot in just a few days.
S多地|W家L用@N方式碛算地球的年o
Many geologists tried this method to calculate the age of the earth.
他勘探了大They used the Grand Canyon
有地球上其他的沉e^域
and other sedimentary sequences around the planet.
但是他的Y差so法y一
But their answers ranged too widely to be of much use,
差300f年到150|年
anywhere between three million years and 15 billion.
@方法有其他的}
And there were other problems with this method:
即使最下拥难沂
Even the deepest layers of rock
也不是地球上最古老的|西
are not the oldest things on earth.
因榧词寡沂也不能牡厍蜃畛跛受的碾y中存
Why? Because not even rocks could survive the earth's violent infancy.
而太空 那又是另一回事
In space it's another story.
地球Q生r留下了任何的o念品
Are there any mementos from when the earth was born,
有可以C明真年g的物w
objects that could possibly tell us its true age?
我知道一地方 可以找到年太系形成r
I know a place where the unused bricks and mortar left over
留的zE
from the creation of our solar system can be found.
它存在於木星和火星的道g
It lies between the orbits of Jupiter and Mars.
@些是a生地球的原料
Here is the stuff of the newborn earth,
它在冰冷的太空中h
adrift in cold storage, unchanged
奈锤淖^
ever since that time.
100f年左右之前
A million or so years ago,
一w大的小行星恰巧糇擦艘活w^小的
a large asteroid happened to jostle a much smaller one,
⑺推到一新的道
sending it on a new trajectory,
它的\榆E在大s5f年前的一夜晚KY
a collision course that ended one night some 50,000 years ago.
它奶炜^打破了大It must have shattered the peace of the Grand Canyon as it sailed overhead...
撞粜纬蛇@大坑
to blast out this crater
即大{谷所在的州
在後磉@Y被Q 利桑那
in what would one day be known as Arizona.
@wF|小行星的碎片
Fragments of the iron asteroid that made this crater
被完整的保留了下
have survived intact.
如果我知道@KF的形成rg
If we just knew how long ago that iron was forged,
我就能知道太系的年g
we'd know the age of the solar system.
也包括地球
Including the earth.
怎N才能知道呢
But how could we know that?
挑K石^
Pick a rock.
S便一K石^
Any rock.
@怎N
How about that one?
@K石^中的某些原子可能具有放射性
Some atoms in this rock could be radioactive,
它自然地l生衰
which means they spontaneously disintegrate
亩成其他元素
and become other elements.
原子首先成Q原子
A uranium atom first becomes a thorium atom.
平均而言 耗r十|年
On average, it takes a few billion years.
Q很不定
The thorium is much more unstable.
不到一月的rg就能成h
In less than a month it turns into protactinium.
一分後 h又成了其他元素
A minute later, protactinium becomes something else.
又^10次的核D
The atom undergoes ten more nuclear transmutations...
淼剿プ的最後一h
Until it reaches the last stop on the decay chain:
衰指的是放射性衰^程中成a生的一系列衰a物
一定的U原子
A stable atom of lead.
U⒉辉侔l生化
And lead it will remain... For eternity.
20世o有巨大的成就  在资年Y
In the 20th century there was a huge effort, lasting decades,
y量每N放射性元素D成另一N元素所用的rg後
to measure the time it takes for each radioactive element to transmute into another element.
物理W家lF每不定元素的原子
Physicists discovered that the atoms of each unstable element
衰比率是a定的
decay at a constant rate.
原子的原子核就像一座}殿
The nucleus of an atom is a kind of sanctuary,
o震雍铜h境的改
immune to the shocks and upheavals of its environment.
用N子砸
Hit it with a hammer.
在油Y炸
Boil it in oil.
饣它
Vaporize it.
原子走的不o不慢
The nuclear clock goes on ticking,
每一跳的rg都^
keeping an absolute standard of time
不日月星辰的化
that does not look to the sun and the stars.
要t解地球真的年g ]有比y量原子更好的k法了
What better way to find the true age of the earth than with the uranium atom?
只要知道岩石中衰成U的比率
If you knew what fraction of the uranium in a rock had turned into lead,
就可以算出岩石存在了多久
you could calculate how much time had passed since the rock was formed
但有}
But there's a problem.
形成之初的那些岩石
The rocks in the earth that were present when it was formed
都已不痛嬖
are no more.
或被核榱 或被融化了 或者被重塑了
They've all been crushed, melted, remade.
有k法可以算出U的最初盗
There is a way to calculate the amount of lead that was present from the beginning.
天n的Y物
It's a gift from the heavens:
E石
Meteorites.
@K碎片碜栽斐蛇@大坑的E石 很理想
This one... A fragment of the one that made this giant crater... Was ideal
@KE石中U的含量
The amount of lead deep inside this meteorite
c地球形成r的完全一
is exactly the same as when earth formed.
既然知道了衰的固定比率
Since you know the constant rate of uranium decay,
就可以知道@KE石的年g
that should give you the age of the meteorite,
和地球的年g一
which was made at the same time as the earth.
只要y量
All you had to do was measure
E石中的U就行了
the amount of lead in meteorites.
很伟
Easy, right?
一位在芝加哥大W名叫哈理森・布朗的科W家
A scientist named Harrison Brown at the University of Chicago,
1947年首次掌握了@方法
first understood this in 1947.
他x窳艘晃谎芯可H操作 克R・彼得森
He chose a young graduate student, Clair Patterson, to do the work.
r彼得森怎N也不想到@作I
Patterson couldn't possibly know how this assignment
改他的一生
would alter the course of his life...
有@世界
And ours.
表面上只是渭的科W研究
What seemed like pure scientific research
Y果s不
turned out to be so much more.
克R・彼得森 酆扇A州一位]fT的鹤
Clair Patterson, son of a letter carrier from Iowa,
天性叛逆 W校表F一般
was rebellious by nature and not very good in school.
但他s是天生的科W家
But he was a natural born scientist.
一位名叫哈里森・布朗的地|W家
A geologist named Harrison Brown
交o彼得森一看似蔚目W作I
gave Patterson what seemed like a straightforward scientific assignment
首先 派特
First off, Pat...
你不介意我叫你派特吧
You mind if I call you Pat?
我知道你不是地|W家
Now, I know you're no geologist...
很可能分不清L石和花岩
probably couldn't tell granite from feldspar...
但我f你使用|Vx很在行
but I hear you really know your way around a mass spectrometer, Pat
很好 Y婚了
Good. You married, Pat?
Y了 她叫谌 也是研究化W的
Yeah, Laurie. Yeah, she-she's a chemist, too.
我曾在橡X一起槁哈D工作^
Uh, we worked on the Manhattan Project together,at Oak Ridge
第二次世界大鹌陂g研lcu造原子的一大型事工程
好 很好 首先你要t解
Good. Okay, well, first thing you need to know:
@些被Q殇石的小晶w
There are these tiny crystals called zircons.
非常小 尖大小 Yo密 杂
Real small, size of a pinhead, tight as a drum and tough.
定性O高
Nothing gets in or out of 'em.
资|年如一日
And I'm talking for billions of years.
我通^Π含它的岩石年份y定 得知了它的年份
We know how old these grains are because we've already dated the rocks they came from.
每石只含有百f分之椎拟
Each little zircon has only a few parts per million
而@些又M一步衰
of uranium inside, and that uranium is decaying
更少量的U
to even tinier amounts of lead.
只要y量出U的含量
Now, you figure out how to measure that lead,
就能知道E石的年代
and you'll know how to do it for a meteorite.
你能做到
You think you can do that, Pat?
可以 ]}
Yeah. Yeah, I... I don't see why not.
很好 如果你做到了 你就是第一知道地球年g的人
Good, because when you do, you'll be the first man to know the age of the earth.
你就出名了
And you'll be famous.
很蔚
And you'll see: It'll be easy.
易如反掌
Duck soup.
彼得森在y量石微粒中的微量Ur
While Patterson tried to measure the trace amounts of lead in the zircon grains
另外一位名叫讨蔚D的研究生
another grad student, George Tilton,
也在y定石中的含量
was measuring the amount of uranium in the same grains.
彼得森只要U含量做等精度y量就可以
All Patterson had to do was measure the amount of lead with equal accuracy
即保持y量l件不
交o你了 派特
She's all yours, Pat.
y了6次 Y果相同
Measured it six times. Same result:
百f分之3.2
3.2 parts per million.
好的 讨 x啦
Yeah, nice going, George, thanks.
迪D的Y果每次都是一拥
Tilton's results were always the same.
但是彼得森y量相同微粒的U含量的Y果s差e很大
But Patterson's results on the lead content of the same grains were wildly inconsistent
]道理啊
This made no sense.
有可能是因橐郧昂U污染了室
Could the lab have been contaminated by previous experiments with lead?
或S是自然界中
Maybe it was the naturally high amounts
高含量的U影了Y果
of lead in the environment that were messing up his results.
彼得森用M了k法清除室的U
Patterson did everything he could to cleanse the lab of any lead
翟箩
U含量是超出了100倍
There was still 100 times too much lead.
他已花M了2年多的rg
He had been at it for more than two years.
易如反掌鬼啊
Duck soup, my ass.
禁止入
彼得森意R到他必用酸碇笕萜骱凸ぞ
Patterson realized he would have to boil his containers and tools in acid
K且提化W原料 以M一步的降低室中的U
and purify all his chemicals to further reduce the lead in his lab
不要啊 噢 我是新淼
Hey, you... Oh, I... No! I'm new here
所在哪
Uh, where's the men's room?
鬼
Ugh damn it.
不彼得森怎硬料聪毒
All of Patterson's obsessive scouring and sterilizing
都]能蚪Q}
had still not solved the problem.
他必念^_始O建造他自己的室
He would need to design his own lab and build it from scratch.
哈里森布朗D去位於帕_迪The opportunity arose when Harrison Brown moved
C出F了
to the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena
他邀彼得森同行
and invited Patterson to join him.
加州理工W院
禁止入
警告 o菌h境
限制^域 只S人TM入
好了 姆 可以了
Okay, Tom, that's enough.
我F在可以M去了
We can move through the interlock, now.
彼得森在@目上已花M了6年rg
Patterson had now been at it for six years,
猿植恍傅恼业K消缌嗽S多x器
doggedly tracking down and eliminating the many sources of lead
造成影的U的源^
that were compromising his instruments.
他建造了世界上第一超Q室
He had built the world's first ultra-clean room.
他K於可以y量出岩石中U的_切含量
He was finally able to measure how much lead was actually in the rock
岩石的年代已_定了
One whose age had already been established.
彼得森K於可以利用@KFE石
Now, at last, Patterson was ready to tackle the iron meteorite
找出地球的年g
to find the true age of the earth.
他㈦E石颖У桨⒇家室
He brought his meteorite specimen back to the Argonne National Laboratory...
在那Y 世界上最精_的|Vx投入使用
Where the world's most accurate mass spectrometer had just become operational
博士 就不能等到明天
Doc, this can't wait till tomorrow?
好了 小砘 我要把你饣了
Okay, little buddy, we're gonna have to vaporize you.
|Vx利用磁颖局械脑素分x
A mass spectrometer uses magnets to separate the elements contained in a sample
亩使得各N元素可以被量化
so that the amounts of each element can be quantified.
@就是解_地球真年g之i的最後一h
This would provide the last missing piece in the puzzle of the earth's true age
F在 我要把你x子化
Now I'm gonna ionize you, yeah.
]有上去那N可怕
Sounds worse than it is.
小夥伴很H密呦
What's an electron between friends?
杜^了颖颈煌饨绲你U污染後
Having isolated the sample from any outside lead contamination,
彼得森K於可以y量颖局械你U和的含量了
Patterson was, at last, ready to measure the amount of lead and uranium in the sample
K且y定它形成的年代了
and calculate how many years before it had formed.
地球的真年g
The true age of the earth.
感x所有做出^I的科W家
Thank you to all the scientists who came before.
感x地|W家
Thank you, geologists.
感x查斯・R
Thank you, Charles Lyell.
著名地|W家 均f的重要述者
感x~克・法拉第
Thank you, Michael Faraday.
lF磁感
s瑟夫・姆森
J.J. Thomson.
lF子
W人固亍けR瑟福
Ernest Rutherford.
核物理之父
感x哈里森・布朗
Thank you, Harrison Brown.
研究如何分_和
地球的年g是45|q
The world is four and a half billion years old.
我成功了
We did it.
Mom?
Mom.
彼得森想最先把@困_他多年的iF
Patterson wanted his mother to be the first person
c他的母H分享
to know what he had struggled for so many years to discover
地球的真年g
The true age of the earth.
@lF樗硎颤N
His reward for this discovery?
天大的麻
A world of trouble.
他rK不知道
He didn't know it, but he was on a collision course
他妨K了某些世界上最有嗔Φ娜说睦益
with some of the most powerful people on the planet.
於古_R人碚f
To the ancient Romans,
雄サ耐列K不是一地c
the majestic ringed planet Saturn was not a real place,
其卧~也有r神的意思
也不是星球 而是天神
not a world, but a God King,
天地Y合的Y晶
a son of the marriage of heaven and earth,
U神
the God of lead.
@些立柱都是_RV錾献罟爬仙R的zE
These columns are all that remain of this oldest temple in the Roman forum
最早是在2500年前供奉r神
first consecrated to Saturn 2,500 years ago.
後碛米隽_R的金
It also served as Rome's treasury
也做^量局
and its bureau of weights and measures.
今天是古_R的r神
Tonight is Saturnalia,
向r神表示敬意的12月狂g
the wild december holiday in Saturn's honor.
日常生活行氐最倒
And everyday life will be turned upside down.
主人榕W服
The masters will serve the slaves,
停止一切和死刑
no wars or executions will be allowed,
人相互o予Y物
and gifts will be exchanged.
装倌赆
A couple of hundred years from now,
早年g的牧想要吸引更多教徒r
when the early church fathers look for a way to attract more pagans,
他把r神成了}Q
they'll decide to turn Saturnalia into Christmas,
o@冬季的日x予了新的意x
making it the latest in a long line of winter solstice holidays to be re-purposed
在r神的夜晚@高的r神神像看上去好像是@幼
This towering statue of Saturn may have look something like this on the night of saturnalia
但是在古_R 他有更暗的一面
But in ancient Rome, this God had another, darker side.
r神是一冷酷的康男舆t的食乒
That other Saturn is a cold and sullen, sluggish ghoul,
硬泳yl脾
given to irrational bouts of rage.
她λ父H的罪行y以言喻
He committed an unspeakable act of violence against his father,
甚至吞噬了自己的孩子
and devoured his own children.
在所有古人能用肉眼看的行星中
Of all the planets visible to the unaided eyes of the ancients
土星的速度是最慢的
Saturn is the slowest,
@也就是古人用U神的名字樗命名的原因
which could explain why it's named after the God of lead
不可否J的是
But there's no denying
r神性格的暗面
that the more negative aspects of Saturn's personality
其反映的是古代人於U中毒的JR
reflect the age-old knowledge of the symptoms of lead poisoning.
有意思的是
Funny thing about the Romans.
管他知道
Even though they knew
接|U使人中毒
that contact with lead inevitably poisoned people,
造成不育有l狂
rendered them sterile and drove them mad,
你猜他是用的什N材料
what metal did they use to make the pipes
修建他大名鼎鼎的供水管道呢
that carried the water through their legendary aqueducts?
o你提示
I'll give you a hint.
水管@~
The word "plumbing" comes
就是碓挫独丁文Y的 U
from the Latin word for lead, "plumbum."
他用什N金傺u造他的浴缸呢
What metal did they use to line their famous baths?
如果葡萄酒太酸r他怎Nk呢
And how did they sweeten their wines when they were too sour?
他的碗瓢盆又是什N材料呢
What did they use to line their vats and cooking pots?
部分v史W家相信
There are some historians who believe
U的V泛使用是造成
that the widespread use of lead was a major cause
_R帝覆绲闹饕
in the decline and fall of the Roman Empire.
槭颤N他在知道U有毒後^m使用呢
Why did they continue to use lead long after they knew it was toxic?
因樗便宜 延展性好 u造
It was cheap, very malleable, easy to work with,
大量接|致命┝康哪切┤
and the ones who were exposed to it at its most lethal levels...
V工和理U的工人
the miners and workers who processed the lead...
都是oPo要的
were considered expendable.
他的性命不重要
Their lives didn't matter.
他是奴`
They were slaves.
地球上大部分的U最初都是深埋在地下 c生物保持安全的距x
Most of the earth's lead started off at a safe distance from living things, down below the surface
但是大s8500年前
but about 8,500 years ago,
人知道了如何牡匮Y挖|西
humans began figuring out how to dig into the earth
难沂中提金
and extract metals from rock.
@f@新建成r
By the time this villa was new,
也就浊年前
just a couple of thousand years ago,
_R人年aU8f
the romans were producing 80,000 tons of lead a year.
槭颤NUξ的危害@N大
Why is lead so poisonous to us?
因楫UM入我的w
Because when it gets into our bodies,
U假b成其他金 比如\或者F
lead mimics other metals, like zinc and iron,
胞茁殉砷L_需要的元素
the ones our cells actually need to grow and flourish.
胞中的酶被U的窝b迷惑
Enzymes in the cell are fooled by the lead's masquerade,
它_始Y合
and they begin to dance.
@是致命的Y合 因殂Uo法M足
But it's a dance of death, because the lead is an imposter
胞至P重要的需要
that can't fulfill the cell's vital needs.
U也妨K神D物|
Lead also blocks neurotransmitters,
堵塞胞g的交流Wj
the communication network between the cells.
干_τ和W能力至P重要的分子的神末梢
It interferes with the molecular receptors that are vital to memory and learning.
孩童尤橛泻
This is especially damaging to children,
]人可以避免
but lead poisoning spares no one.
倪M入20世o_始
Starting at the turn of the 20th century,
含U油漆S商l萌芽的V告I者向消M者灌
the makers of leaded paint hired the fledgling advertising industry to persuade the consumer
U孩童o害的^念
that lead was child-friendly.
玩具小U兵荷m小孩f
A little toy lead soldier once to the Dutch boy said,
我好多小夥伴身wY都有一cc的U
"we have some fine relations who all contain some lead."
我_派ψ你JR一下ゴ蟮你U家族中
"Why don't you give a party so folks can meet and see
其他的快沸♀钒榘
"the other happy members of the great lead family?"
第一到淼氖强返碾襞
The first one at the party was gay electric light.
他f "我非常亮"
"He said, " I'm very brilliant."
"我在黑夜YWWl光"
"I always shine at night."
"我@N亮可不是因槲业牟Ａь^"
"No little of my brilliance is due to my glass head,"
"光更明亮"
which gives a light much brighter
"其是因槲沂倾U做的"
"because it's made with lead."
一ο鹉zM硗熳『商m小孩的手臂
A pair or rubbers entered and took the Dutch boy's arm.
他f "我你的鞋子保持乾燥和暖和"
They said, " we are protectors who keep you dry and warm.
"u造我的人f"
"You knew when we were molded, the man who made us said,"
"我怨棠陀眠很活"
we're strong and tough and lively
"@是因槲含有U"
"because in us, there's lead."
那r含Ua品]有真正_始大l展
But lead production didn't really shift into high gear
直到20年代早期
until the early 1920's
化W狂人托R斯・米基利夥同投Y人
when chemist Thomas Midgley and inventor.
他也是氟利昂的l明人
通用汽的查斯・P特`
Charles Kettering of General Motors
⑺囊一U以抗爆猷孱^添加到汽油中
found that tetraethyl lead could be marketed as an anti-knock additive to gasoline.
四乙基U在那r用於提高汽油的辛烷值
他成立了乙基公司
They formed a new company called the Ethyl Corporation.
美部曾考]用它做毒
It had once been considered for use as a poison gas by the U.S. war department
和油漆中的U不同 四乙基U是脂溶性的
Unlike the lead in paint, tetraethyl lead was fat soluble.
皮w接|半杯的量就致命
A half a cup of it on your skin could kill you.
生aS家yN量可以_到每年6千f
The manufacturers calculated that they could sell 60 million tons of it a year
只有一}
Only problem was,
一些在特拉A州和新晌髦莨S工作的T工
some of the workers who processed the stuff
得精神失常 出F幻X
in factories in Delaware and New Jersey were going insane, hallucinating,
跳窗而出
jumping out of windows.
死羁植
They died screaming.
@rN售宣餍枰的就不HH是跳舞的襞萘
This was a selling job that would require a lot more than dancing light bulbs
他需要一懂科W的人
What was needed was a man of science
安崦癖的恐慌 K且提升U的形象
to calm the public's fears and improve lead's image.
他找到了一合m的人x
They found the right man for the job.
那也是第一次
This was one of the first times
利用科W嗤碚谘Νh境和公共健康的威that the authority of science was used to cloak a threat to public health and the environment
辛辛那提的一位年p博士 _伯特基W
Robert Kehoe, a young doctor from Cincinnati,
受雇於通用汽
was hired by GM.
他公心的U的危害提出了反g
He raised scientific doubts in the public mind about the dangers of lead
他f U是h境中天然存在的
Lead was naturally occurring in the environment, he said.
_可能Φ谝痪的工人造成I害 但是
Yes, there might be occupational hazards for the people who worked with lead, but
I界自我O管就蛄
that could be best handled by industry self-regulation.
K]有C表明
And there was no evidence to suggest
UοM者成威that lead posed any threat to the consumer.
资年 ]有人反g他
For decades no one challenged him...
直到克R・彼得森_始研究
Until Clair Patterson went searching
地球的年g
for the age of the earth.
克R・彼得森Φ厍蚰挲g的研究
Claire Patterson's research on the age of the earth
使他成槭澜缟y量痕量UI域首屈一指的＜
had made him the world's leading expert on measuring trace amounts of lead
和r的其他人一
And like everyone else at the time,
他猜想U是天然普遍存在的
he assumed the prevalence of lead occurred naturally.
像他@诱嬲的科W家
True scientist that he was, he set out
他_始M全力探究U是如何在h境中鞑サ
to discover everything he could about how lead circulates through the environment.
依靠美石油M的芸
On a grant from the American Petroleum Institute,
他仔的y量了深雍\雍Ｋ中的U舛
he carefully measured the concentrations of lead in deep and shallow seawater
彼得森又一次lF他的原始o法解了
Once again, Patterson found that his initial data made no sense.
深雍Ｋ中只有O少量的U舛
There were only minuscule concentrations of lead in the deep ocean water
但在\水和水面上
But in shallow waters and at the surface,
U舛s要高出装俦
the concentrations of lead were hundreds of times greater.
海洋中 要用装倌\雍Ｋ才c深雍Ｋ相混合
In any ocean, it takes a few hundred years for the shallow waters to mix with the deep.
彼得森得出Y 表雍Ｋ中大量的U是最近才出F的
This told Patterson that the large amount of lead in the surface waters had arrived recently.
否t它分训母均
Otherwise it would have been more evenly distributed.
知道了\拥你U舛纫约芭c深踊旌纤需要的rg
Knowing the quantity of lead in the shallow seas and the time needed to mix it into the deeper layers
他就可以估算出表面的U污染比率
he was able to estimate the rate of lead contamination at the surface.
彼得森自己
Patterson asked himself
是什N能o全球的海洋磉@N多的U
what could possibly supply lead to the world's oceans at such a rate.
@些U都是哪Y淼
Where's all that lead coming from?
我知道了 哈里森
I think I know, Harrison.
它碜院U汽油
It's from leaded gasoline.
好吧 @有c麻 派特
Well, then we've got a problem, Pat,
因槲的Y金都是哪茄Y淼
because that's the same place the money comes from.
但是彼得森]有屈服
But Patterson would not give in.
他立即著手l表Wg文
He went right to work on publishing the scientific paper
含U汽油做出伐
that would make the case against leaded gasoline.
他把文寄o了久盛名的科W期刊
When he sent the paper to the prestigious scientific journal
《自然》 彼得森⒆约旱拿字放在後面
Nature, Patterson put his own name second.
他^去常常@ 椭他的W生提高望
He often did that with his students to advance their reputations
他一子都在避免出L^以及避S之而淼暮锰
He made a lifelong point of shunning the limelight and the privileges that come with it
l表後H3天
Only three days after publication...
反糸_始了
the push-back began.
-你好 彼得森博士 -很高d到你
- Hello, Dr. Patterson. - Pleasure to meet you.
您的研究成果很了不起
Very impressed by your work.
您的研究成果ξ石油化工行I有很大的影
Your work is of great interest to us in the petroleum and chemical industries
多了你的助
Well, it wouldn't have been possible without your funding.
]e 我希望提供o你更多的椭
Precisely. And there's so much more we'd like to do for you.
正好 我想在O地冰又y量U含量
Well, I've been thinking about measuring lead in polar ice
看看是不是和海洋中的Y果一
to see if it shows the same kind of pattern as the oceans.
U 你的工作已Y束了
Lead? But you've already done that.
是r候研究其他微量元素了
We're thinking it's time you move on to other trace elements.
其 彼得森博士
In fact, Dr. Patterson,
我有能力Y助你去o限制地研究其他方面
our ability to fund you in any other line of research is...Virtually limitless.
U是一N神毒素
Lead is a neurotoxin.
你⑺囊一U墓S\出r
When you ship your tetraethyl lead from the factory...
在加M汽油之前
before you add it to the gasoline...
就像是\送化W武器
it's handled just like a chemical weapon.
都是有原因的
There's a reason for that.
你X得@些U呐夤苤信懦鲠岫既チ四难Y呢
Where do you suppose all that lead goes after it leaves the tailpipe
想想@ξ和我的後代造成什N影
Think about what it might be doing to us and our kids.
基W博士已C明了@N程度的U
Dr. Kehoe has shown that the level of lead in the environment
在h境中就如同12月的雪一幼匀
...is as natural as snow in December
那它怎N在深雍Ｋ中存在呢
Then why doesn't it show up in the deep water? Here,
我o你看
let me just show you.
多x了
Thanks for your time.
等等 你要把上百f的毒馀诺轿呼吸的空庵
Wait, you're just gonna keep on putting millions of tons of poison into the air we breathe?
就算我的研究不能使你停a 以後也有科W家可以做到
If my research doesn't put you out of business some future scientist will
石油行I淼馁助一夜之g消失得o影o
Patterson's funding from the oil industry vanished overnight
事上 他要他失I
In fact, they tried to get him fired.
但是美政府  海
But the U.S. government... The Army, the Navy,
原子能委T 公共l生署
the atomic energy commission, the public health service,
有家科W基金 都支持他
and the National Science Foundation... Stood by him,
支持他的U污染研究
supporting his research on lead pollution.
榱苏His investigations took him from Greenland in the far north to Antarctica in the far south
足E遍迅河流c山川
and to rivers, mountains and valleys in between.
即使面ψ毫拥l件
In even the most hostile conditions,
彼得森和他的Ff力}u了
Patterson and his team worked to replicate
om室的o污染h境
the immaculate environment of the clean room.
他每天都更Q塑料制服
Their plastic suits were replaced daily.
在零下囟认轮泄ぷ10-12小r
Working ten-to 12-hour days in subzero weather,
他在南O洲冰又需了深_200英尺的通道
they dug a 200-foot-long shaft into the ice of Antarctica
s61米
那是某N程度上的rg旅行
It was a form of time travel,
取得了那是在工I革命_始前
to recover snow that had fallen three centuries ago,
300年前的雪
before the start of the Industrial Revolution.
你的鼻子
Nose!
快擦鼻子
Wipe your nose, damn it!
你w鹊你U比冰Y的高1千倍
There's a thousand times more lead in you than in this ice!
你@是想要污染整颖
You want to contaminate the whole damn sample?!
^4星期的精疲力M的D苦颖窦工作後
After four grueling weeks of painstaking sample collection
彼得森浠氐室了
Patterson was ready to go back to the lab.
和海水中一 他lF在雪中
As with the oceans, he found that the amount of lead
装倌昵暗你U含量要低得多
was much lower in the snow of a few hundred years before.
不在地球上的其他什N地方
No matter where he searched on earth,
也不管多久以前的颖
no matter how far he traveled back in time,
Y果都f明一件事
the results always told the same story:
^去空夂退中天然存在的含量要低得多得多
The naturally occurring levels in the air and water in the past, were far lower.
浊年 人都知道
For thousands of years, lead had been known
U造成Xp 影l育
to cause brain damage, developmental impairment,
暴力行 甚至致命
violent behavior, and even death.
在地球年g的研究中
In searching for the age of the earth,
彼得森o意中lF了一隹涨耙模的毒害污染的C
Patterson had stumbled on the evidence for a mass poisoning on an unprecedented scale.
但是基W和其他受雇於U工I的科W家
But Kehoe and the other scientists employed by the lead industry
裾f民o需榇心
persuaded the public they had nothing to worry about.
所有人都J楸说蒙是_子
Everyone thought Patterson was a crank
直到有人_始P注@}
Until one man started to pay attention.
彼得森⑺的lF公鸯侗
Patterson went public with his discoveries about lead in a big way
他把研究Y果l表在主要的h境健康期刊上
He published his findings in a major environmental health journal
也寄o了多位政府高
and sent copies to various government leaders,
包括一位很有影力的⒆hT
including one highly influential senator.
因州⒆hT埃德蒙・R斯基
Edmund Muskie of Maine
是r任的⒆h院大馀c水污染委T主席
was the chairman of the senate subcommittee on air and water pollution
1966年他主持了P於U}的C
In 1966 he held hearings on the lead question.
第一位C人
The first witness
_伯特基W 含U汽油L期以淼闹С终
was Dr. Robert Kehoe, longtime scientific advocate for leaded gasoline
你的Y是不是 1937年到F在
Is it, uh, your conclusion that, in 1937 to the present time, there has been
普通no increase in the amount of lead
有加油站工作人T拇庵形入的
taken in from the atmosphere by the average traffic policeman,
U的盗]有增加
service station attendant, or... Or motorist?
根本]有C
There is not the slightest evidence
可以C明@段rg
that there has been a change in this picture
有任何改
during this period of time.
完全]有
Not the slightest.
C召_的rg
The hearings were scheduled to take place,
特地x在彼得森在南O洲的rg
when the fiercest critic, Claire Patterson was off in Antarctica.
但是他出人意料地
But he unexpectedly appeared
在第五天出席了
on the fifth day of testimony.
看上去好像人w中U舛鹊脑黾
Uh, looks like there seems to be an increase in the concentration of lead in people
是ch境接|的Y果
as a result of exposure to the environment.
是@
Is that correct?
是的
That is correct.
至於b定典型性德U含量
In identifying typical lead levels,
你用的是地窦的y量Y果
you use actual measurements you've taken in the field?
是的
Yes.
@些zyY果
Are these observations different
c其他C人提出的有^e
from the ones we've been hearing about from other witnesses?
]有 Y果是相同的
No, th... They're the same observations.
你 你的C~是f
You... You've testified that there has been
自然U含量]有化 是@
no change in natural lead levels, is that correct?
是的
That is correct.
你_定
You're sure about that?
非常肯定
Absolutely.
F在人w中的含量看似很こ
The levels we see in people today may be typical.
但^不代表它是天然的
But they are not by any means natural.
你J同基W博士的
So you don't disagree with Dr. Kehoe's numbers?
J同
Uh, no, no.
你是f 根相同的
You're saying that the same numbers
得出了不同的Y
are leading to different conclusions?
是的
Yes.
@N 通常是
You know, this is the kind of thing
律f的 不是科W家
we expect to hear from lawyers, not scientists.
我也是@NJ
I would agree with that, yes.
基W博士 你好像δ愕慕Y很有把握
You seem to be very sure of your conclusions, Dr. Kehoe.
因槲沂悄壳霸谶@I域最有的
It so happens that I have more experience in this field than anyone else alive
@N含量的Uθ梭w有乐氐拈L期害
At these levels, lead is a severe chronic insult to the human body
]有tWC@示 U危害公健康
There is no medical evidence that lead has introduced a danger to public health.
挖掘装偃f有毒物|K⑵
It's irresponsible to mine millions of tons
散训江h境中 是O其不任的
of toxic material and disperse it into the environment!
如果真的有C 我早就lF了
If there was proof of harm, we would have found it.
你以U牟利 然不⒄Y果公T於世
Not if your purpose is to sell lead.
彼得森c整行I又抗了20年
Patterson fought the industry for another 20 years
U才被禁止在美消M品中使用
before lead was finally banned in U.S. consumer products.
@位找出地球年g的人
The man who figured out the age of the earth
同右苍炀土20世o
was also responsible for one
最ゴ蟮墓健康}的倮
of the greatest public health victories of the 20th century.
短短啄觊g 和平均
In just a few years, average lead levels
血液U含量猛降百分之75
in the blood of children plummeted by some 75%.
如今 tW界的共R是
Today, the medical consensus is unanimous...
人w鹊你U含量不是o毒 只是量很少而已
there's no such thing as a nontoxic level of lead in humans, however small
F在 科W家又l出了其他h境}的警告
Today, scientists sound the alarm on other environmental dangers
既得利益Fw依然l蛩自己的科W家以混淆
Vested interests still hire their own scientists to confuse the issue.
但是到^
But in the end,
最K的受害者 又是l呢
nature will not be fooled.